Chapter 109. Ahab and Starbucks in the cabin.
According to usage, they were pumping the ship the next morning, and low, no
inconsiderable oil came up with the water. The casks below must have sprung
a bad leak. Much concern was shown, and Starbucks went down into the cabin to
report this unfavorable affair.
Footnote. In sperm whalemen with any considerable quantity of oil on board,
it is a regular semi-weekly duty to conduct a hose into the hold and drench
the casks with seawater, which afterwards at varying intervals is
removed by the ship's pumps. Hereby the casks are sought to be kept damply
tight, while by the changed character of the withdrawn water, the mariners
readily detect any serious leakage in the precious cargo. End of footnote.
Now from the south and west the Peekquad was drawing nigh to Formosa and the
Bashi Isles between which lies one of the tropical outlets from the China
waters into the Pacific. And so Starbucks found Ahab with a general
chart of the oriental archipelos spread before him and another separate one
representing the long eastern coasts of the Japanese islands. Nephon, Matsmi,
and Sikoke. With his snow white new ivory leg braced against the screwed leg
of his table, and with a long pruning hook of a jack knife in his hand, the
wondrous old man, with his back to the gangway door, was wrinkling his brow and
tracing his old courses again. Who's there? Hearing the footstep at the door,
but not turning round to it. On deck, be gone. Captain Ahab mistakes. It is I.
The oil in the hold is leaking, sir. We must upd
now that we are nearing Japan. Heave two here for a week to tinker a parcel of
old hoops. Either do that, sir, or waste in one day more oil than we may make
good in a year. What we come 20,000 mi
to get is worth saving, sir. So it is.
So it is if we get it. I was speaking of
the oil in the hold, sir. And I was not speaking or thinking of that at all. Be
gone. Let it leak. I'm all a leak myself. I leaks and leaks. Not only full
of leaky casks, but those leaky casks are in a leaky ship. And that's a far
worse plight than the Peekquad's man.
Yet I don't stop to plug my leak, or who
can find it in the deep loaded hull, or how hope to plug it, even if found in
this life's howling gale. Starbucks, I'll not have the Burton's hoisted.
What will the owners say, sir? Let the owners stand on Nantucket Beach and out
yell the typhoons. What cares, Ahab?
Owners. Owners. Thou art always praying to me, Starbucks, about those miserly
owners, as if the owners were my conscience. But look ye, the only real
owner of anything is its commander, and Harky, my conscience is in this ship's keel, on deck.
Captain Ahab, said the reening mate, moving further into the cabin with a
daring so strangely respectful and cautious that it almost seemed not only
every way seeking to avoid the slightest outward manifestation of itself, but
within also seemed more than half distrustful of itself.
A better man than I might well pass over in thee, what he would quickly enough
resent in a younger man. I and in a happier Captain Ahab. Devils, dust thou
then so much as dare to critically think of me? On deck? Nay, sir, not yet. I do
intreat, and I do dare, sir, to be forebearing.
Shall we not understand each other better than hitherto, Captain Ahab?
Ahab seized a loaded musket from the rack forming part of most South Seaman's
cabin furniture and pointing it towards Starbucks exclaimed, "There is one god
that is lord over the earth and one captain that is lord over the peekquad on deck."
For an instant, in the flashing eyes of the mate and his fiery cheeks, you would
have almost thought that he had really received the blaze of the leveled tube,
but mastering his emotion, he half calmly rose, and as he quitted the
cabin, paused for an instant, and said, "Thou hast outraged, not insulted me,
sir. But for that I ask thee not to beware of Starbucks. Thou wouldst but
laugh. But let Ahab beware of Ahab.
Beware of thyself, old man.
He waxes brave, but nevertheless obeys.
Most careful bravery that, murmured Ahab as Starbucks disappeared. What's that?
He said, Ahab, beware of Ahab. There's something there. Then unconsciously
using the musket for a staff with an iron brow, he paced to and fro in the
little cabin, but presently the thick pleats of his forehead relaxed, and
returning the gun to the rack, he went on deck.
"Thou art but too good a fellow, Starbucks," he said lowly to the mate.
Then raising his voice to the crew, "Furl the Tagalan sails, and close reef
the top sails for an aft. back the mainard up burton and break out in the main hold.
It were perhaps vain to surmise exactly why it was that as respecting Starbucks
Ahab thus acted. It may have been a flash of honesty in him, or a mere
credential policy which, under the circumstance, imperiously forbad the
slightest symptom of open disaection, however transient, in the important
chief officer of his ship. However it was, his orders were executed, and the
Burton were hoisted.